...prabhuji was saying the statue,
you used the word statue.
讲过雕像 你们用单词statue(雕像)
You see, normally
通常 在印度传统中
when it’s referred
to a holy figure
当谈到一个圣像时
in the Hindu tradition we
don’t use the word statue.
我们不用单词statue(雕像)
We use the word
我们用单词
murti, vigraha or
in English, deity.
murti(圣像) vigraha 或者用英文单词deity(神像)
You see? Because statue,
these are statues
你瞧 因为雕像 这些雕像
which are just there
for decoration,
仅仅在那是为了装饰
you see. Of course, it’s an angel,
you know, but it’s lifeless.
当然 它是个天使 但它是无生命的
It’s just a piece of
plastic, nothing else.
它只是一块塑料 别无其他
So, it will come to a question,
say, yes, also the stone
所以 将会有一个问题 说 是的 圣像
which the murti is made of,
the deity is made of stone,
也是由石头组成的 神像是有石头组成的
no? The difference is,
不是吗 区别在于
you see, when we say Prana
Pratishta: Prana means the life force,
当我们说Prana Pratishta：Prana意味着生命力
Pratishta means
installing the life force.
Pratishta意味着注入生命力
When one is doing the prayer
当一个人在做着注入生命力的祈祷
of installing this life force,
it doesn’t mean that God is not there.
它不意味着神不在那里
God is present everywhere,
in all His creation He is present.
神出现在任何地方 出现在所有祂的创造之中
But what is happening
during Prana Pratishta,
但在注入生命力仪式的过程中发生了什么
the Lord is more alive
within the heart of men.
神在人们的心中更加的有生机
Within your heart He is active.
Within creation He is inactive.
在你的心中祂是活着的 在圣像中祂不是活着的
So, a stone can’t attain Krishna.
A stone can’t attain Narayana,
所以 一个石头不能达到奎师那
一个石头不能达到那罗延
but Narayana is
in that stone also.
但是那罗延也在那石头中
Narayana is in the animals,
but they can’t attain Him.
那罗延在动物体内 但是他们不能达到祂
But whereas, humans
can attain Him.
然而 人类可以达到祂
But humans are fools
sometimes due to Maya.
但是由于摩耶人们有时是愚蠢的
So, Prana Pratishta,
所以 注入生命力仪式
not everybody can
do Prana Pratishta.
不是每个人都能做注入生命力仪式
Firstly, you have to understand
that. There are many people,
首先 你必须理解那 有很多人
many priests who say, "Yes, we have
done the prayer of Prana Pratishta,
很多牧师说 是的 我们已经做了注入生命力仪式的祈祷
that’s it, you know, the murti is blessed
and..." Of course, through your faith
就是那样 你知道的 圣像被祝福了 当然 通过你的信心
the deity is blessed. You are praying, you are
worshipping, because in the Hindu tradition
神像被祝福了 你正在祈祷 你正在做礼拜 因为在印度的传统中
we don’t see any difference
between the deity and God.
我们视神像和神是无差别的
We worship the deity the
same as worshipping God
我们崇拜神像和崇拜神是一样的
due to that blessing, due to that
infusing of that life force inside it.
因为那祝福 因为那内在生命力的灌注
So, that essence
we are worshipping.
所以 那我们崇拜的本质
We are not
worshipping the stone.
我们不是在崇拜石头
We are worshipping the essence
of God which is present everywhere.
我们崇拜神出现在任何地方的本质
So, during the prayer, there are
many mantras which are chanted.
所以 在祈祷的过程中 有很多颂歌被唱诵
While chanting
these mantras
当唱诵这些颂歌时
those who have faith,
they are invoking
那些有信心的人他们在呼唤
the Lord to take seat,
to manifest Himself
神坐下来 去显现祂自己
from their heart to the deity. So, asking
the Lord which is inside of you
从他们的心到圣像 所以 请求你内在的神
to take, to manifest Himself
in the outside so that you can
去接受 在外面显现祂自己所以你可以
build a relationship, an easy
relationship one to one.
建立一个关系 一个简单的一对一的关系
Very often you see people,
yes, look for God inside of you,
通常你看人们 是的 寻找你内在的神
but which part of you, you will look for God?
Where would you look for God? In your heart?
但哪部分的你 你将寻找神 你在哪里寻找神 在你的心中
No, you can’t find
God in your heart.
不 你不能在你的心中找到神
Otherwise doctor
would have already found
否则医生已经找到了
and take Him out and put Him
in a small bottle and give it to you.
并把祂拿出来并将祂放在一个小瓶子中并给你
He is not there.
祂不在那
So, where to find Him?
所以 哪里能找到祂
He is in your spiritual heart.
But your spiritual heart is not visible.
祂在你的心中 但是你的心是不可见的
It’s not a place where you say,
yes, of course, through
它不是你说的地方 是的 当然 通过
certain texts say,
yes, it is here
某些文献 是的 在这里
in the middle, not on the
left side, but in the middle.
正中间 不是在左边 是在正中间
But this is an energy
point, you see,
但是这里是个能量点
your spiritual heart
is an energy point
你的心是一个能量点
and within that energy
point the Lord resides.
并且神居住在那能量内
So, how small He is.
所以 祂是如此的小
Here out of love He
made Himself the smallest
这里出于爱祂把祂自己变成最小
and abides within
His creation
并停留在祂的创造中
and at the same time
we are all in Him.
同时我们都在祂里面
You see, when we chant, for example,
Om Namo Narayanaya.
当我们唱诵 Om Namo Narayanaya
The mantra Om Namo Narayanaya,
this is our mantra, no?
颂歌 Om Namo Narayanaya 这是我们的颂歌 不是吗
This mantra has a
great secret in it.
颂歌里有一个很大的秘密
In itself it reminds mankind
of what is one’s duty here.
在它自己里面-它提醒着一个人他的的职责
One’s duty is to
attain the Lord.
一个人的职责是去到达神
Why we have to attain the Lord?
Because we are eternally bound to Him.
为什么我们必须到达神 因为我们永远与祂相连
This is our core duty. The rest
is just a game, a drama,
这是我们的主要的责任 剩下的只是游戏 喜剧
a drama which
we think it is real,
我们认为一个戏剧是真实的
and due to that how many times you
have think that you have done this drama.
并且由于那 有多少次你认为你已经完成了这个戏剧
Still you keep doing it, you keep thinking,
"Yes, I will be happy in this world.
你还是继续做它 你一直认为 是的 我将在这个世界上变得快乐
If I get this, I will be happy,
If I get that, I will be happy.
如果我得到这个 我将会快乐
如果我得到那个 我将会快乐
If I have that person next to me, I will be happy.
If I have this person next to me, I will be happy.
如果那个人在我旁边 我将会快乐
如果这个人在我旁边 我将会快乐
How many lives have you done the same drama?
How many lives have you played the same role?
有多少世你完成了同样的戏剧 有多少世你扮演者同样的角色
How many lives have you gone for
pilgrimage, just merely physically?
有多少世你去向朝圣之旅 仅仅是纯粹的体力上的
How many times have you chanted
the Name of God just hypocritically
有多少次你唱诵神名仅仅是假惺惺地
the tongue is chanting
without you feeling anything?
用舌头在唱诵 没有你的任何其他知觉
Countless of lives
you have done that.
你已经做过那了无数世
Not one life.
Thousands of lives!
不是一次生命 成千上万世
But why have you not
attained that supreme bliss?
但是为什么你没有到达那最高的喜悦
Because once you would have attained that
supreme bliss, you will eternally dwell with the Lord.
因为一旦你已经到达那最高的喜悦 你将永远和神同在
Because you are looking for Him
elsewhere when He is seated within you.
因为你正在其他地方找祂时祂就坐在你里面
And how to attain Him? Is only when your
mind runs towards Him, not your heart.
并且如何达到祂 只有当你的头脑朝向祂跑时而不是你的心
Very often people say,
"Yes, you know, my heart."
人们经常说 是的 我知道 我的心
You don’t have control over your heart,
but you have control over your mind.
你不能控制你的心 但是你可以控制你的头脑
That’s why Krishna said in the Gita,
"Surrender your mind to Me
那就是为什么奎师那在薄伽梵歌中说 放下你的头脑臣服于我
and I shall take care of everything."
He didn’t say, "Surrender your body",
我将照顾一切 祂没有说 放下你的身体
He didn’t say,
"Surrender your senses",
祂没有说 放下你的感官
He didn’t say surrender anything else,
He didn’t say surrender your soul.
祂没有说放下其他一切 祂没有说放下你的灵魂
How can you hold your soul and surrender
it? You can’t. You belong to Him already.
你怎么能留着你的灵魂并丢掉它 你不能 你已经属于祂
What He said? "Surrender
your mind upon to Me."
祂说了什么 向我臣服你的头脑
That’s why, when there is a deity
outside, it’s easy to surrender the mind.
那就是为什么 当那里有个外在的神像 就比较容易放下头脑
When you have an image outside,
it’s easy to surrender the mind.
当你有个外在的形象 就比较容易放下头脑
Because you are material, no? That body,
you have a mind, you have a body,
因为你是物质的 不是吗 那身体 你有一个头脑 你有一个身体
you have emotions, you have
intellect, you have senses:
你有情感 你有智力 你有感官
they are all material,
他们都是物质的
and the mind runs
towards the material.
并且头脑朝着物质奔跑
This is the nature of
the mind. The mind
这是头脑的天性 头脑
runs where there
is personal benefit.
朝着个人利益的地方跑
Where you get your personal
benefit, you will run there.
哪里能得到你的个人好处你就跑到哪里
This is the
greediness of men.
这是人类的贪婪
So,
所以
the deity is a reminder
of the presence of God,
神像就是神的出现的提醒
where the mind
has to be focused.
是头脑必须专注的地方
So, Prana Pratishta
所以 注入生命力
is the ritual into
reminding oneself
是提醒一个人它自己的仪式
that this is the
presence of God.
这就是神的显现
There are many things what
happen during the Prana Pratishta,
很多事情发生在注入生命力仪式的过程中
even if it is just a mantra
or if it is just a symbol,
即使它只是一个颂歌或者它只是一个符号
but the Lord really
gives His presence.
但是神真的显现了
There was a saint
in Rajasthan, actually,
在拉贾斯坦邦(印度西部的邦)有一个圣人 真的
some years back.
几年前
He is a great
devotee of Krishna.
他是奎师那的伟大的奉献者
So, one day there was
a big Prana Pratishta.
所以 一天有一个大型的生命力注入的仪式
So, the priest was chanting
all the Vedic mantras,
所以 神父正在唱诵所有的吠陀颂歌
and after finish chanting the mantras,
of course, we do all the prayers, all these things,
在完成唱诵颂歌后 当然 我出门做所有的祷告 所有的这些事情
then we do arati, so everybody was
bowing down in front of the deity,
接着我们做arati 所以每个人都在神像前鞠躬
but the saint refused to bow down.
They said, "Why?" He said,
但是圣人拒绝鞠躬 他们说 为什么 他说
"Krishna is not yet inside
of him, inside of the deity."
奎师那还没有在他里面 没有在神像里
They said, "How do you know?" He said,
"I’ll show you." So, he took a piece of cotton,
他们说 你怎么知道的 他说 我将展示给你 所以 他拿了一块棉花
placed it in front
of the nostril of the
放在了神像
deity,
的鼻孔中
nothing. You see, if you put
a cotton in front of your nose,
什么都没发生 如果你把一块棉花放在你的鼻子面前
you know, this is how they test also if
somebody is still alive or is gone, you know.
你知道 这就是他们如何测试某个人是活着还是死了
So, the cotton
is so fine that
所以 棉花没有动 哪怕
if any little bit of
breath, it will move.
一丁点的呼吸 它就会移动
So, nothing. So, then the saint said,
"Thakurji is there. Krishna is there
所以 什么也没发生 所以 接着圣人说  塔库里在那里 奎师那在那里
and I am asking Him to
please, bless the deity,
并且我请求祂 祝福这个神像
enter into the deity."
So, he saw Krishna entering the deity.
进入这个神像 所以 他看到奎师那进入这个神像
So, when he saw Krishna entering the deity,
he said, "Here, you will see the difference."
所以当他看见奎师那进入这个神像 他说 这里 你将看到不同
Then this time when
he put the cotton, He was
接着这一次当他放置了棉花 祂
inhaling and exhaling.
So, the cotton would move.
在呼吸和吸气 所以 棉花可以移动
So, like that, you see, through
the mantras, through the prayers,
所以 像那样 你瞧 通过颂歌 通过祈祷
through the faith of the people especially,
through the faith of the people,
主要通过通过人们的信心 通过人们的信心
a mere statue which is made
of stone is transformed into
一个纯粹由石头做的雕像可以转化成
a vigraha, a deity.
一个圣像 一个神像
So, this is Prana Pratishta where the live
force, you know, God’s life force is flowing
所以 这就是生命里注入仪式中的生命能量 神的生命力在流动
and that place doesn’t stay just a place,
because the place becomes a temple,
那不会呆在一个地方 因为这地方是一个寺庙
this is a temple where God resides, because
the temple is not just a place like every place.
这就是神居住的寺庙 因为寺庙不是一个像其他地方的地方
You can say, yes, for some people,
they can find God everywhere,
你能说 是的 对于一些人 他们能在任何地方找到神
but why do you think that temples are special?
Because temples are energy places,
但是你为什么认为寺庙是特殊的 因为寺庙是具有能量的地方
energy point where
you can meet the Lord,
你能遇见神的能量点
where He makes it easy
for you to connect with Him.
祂很容易让你和祂连接的地方
Otherwise, elsewhere
it would be more difficult.
另外 其它地方会更加困难
You can say, "Yes, I’m going to
nature." Very often you will hear
你可以说 是的 我将走向自然 通常你会听到
people say, "Yes, I am going to walk
in the nature, I feel more connected
人们说 是的 我们要走在大自然中 我感到与神有更多的连接
to God." Yeah, but you feel connected to
nature, but you don’t feel connected to God.
是的 但是你会感到与大自然有更多的连接 你不会感到与神连接
This is the mistake that
people do very often.
这就是人们犯的错误
God is superior to nature.
神是高于大自然的
He is superior to Maya. Everything
else is Maya. Everything.
祂高于摩耶 其他一切都是摩耶 一切
Your mind is Maya, your body is Maya, your
senses are Maya, your emotions are Maya,
你的头部是摩耶 你的身体是摩耶 你的感官是摩耶 你的情感是摩耶
the whole creation is Maya,
整个创造是摩耶
but the Lord is superior to that.
Maya doesn’t touch Him.
但是神是高于那 摩耶触及不到祂
So, what is inside of you which
is linked to Him? It is your Atma.
所以 你内在的什么连接着祂 是你的灵魂
Only your Atma has
connection with Bhagavan.
只有你的灵魂连接着神
So, when your mind alters itself,
when your mind transforms itself,
所以 当你的头脑改变了它自己 当你的头脑转变了它自己
when your mind changes
from the materialistic way,
当你的头脑从物质化的方式改变
with the mind which is always
running towards the outside,
头脑总是试图跑向外在
that mind which is like a monkey
which is jumping from one desire to the
头脑像一只猴子从一个欲望跳到另一个 认为那
others thinking that, "Yes, I will be happy",
when that mind transforms into Divine,
是的 我将会快乐 当那头脑转向神
that mind itself becomes
头脑它自己变得
the way to the Lord.
That’s what Krishna said,
通向神的方式   那就是奎师那说的
"A controlled mind is your best friend and
an uncontrolled mind is your worst enemy."
一个掌控了的头脑是你最好的朋友同时一个没有被掌控的头脑是你最坏的敌人
So, it is the same mind.
所以 它是同一个头脑
In one go it is positive and another
it is negative. When it is filled
一方面是积极的同时另一方面是消极的 当它被
with favorable emotions, it becomes love. When it
is filled with negative emotions, it becomes hate.
良好的情绪所填充时 它变成爱 当它被负面情绪填充时 它变成恨
But mind is still the same.
There is only one.
但头脑始终是相同的 那只有一个
You understand? That
你理解了吗 那
when you go to a temple, it is
that mind that has to surrender.
当你去一个寺庙 你的头脑就必须被丢下